教 父 第三部
亲爱的孩子们
My dear children...
我迁居纽约已有多年
it is now better than several years since I moved to New York
但不能如愿常见你们
and I haven't seen you as much as I would like to.
但愿你们前来观礼
I hope you will come to this ceremony of papal honors
教皇圣谕褒奖我行善
given for my charitable work
纽约 1979年
世上唯有子女是财宝
The only wealth in this world is children.
人间财权难以比拟
More than all the money, power on earth
你们是我的至宝
you are my treasure.
安东尼 玛莉
Anthony and Mary
为了你们能更好地成长
although I entrusted your education to your mother for your own best interests
我将你们托付给你们的母亲
you know how I look forward to seeing you
我无时无刻都想和你们重聚天伦
and to a new period of harmony in our lives.
也许你们能说动母亲来观礼
Perhaps you might prevail upon your mother to come to this celebration
并且时常参加家庭聚会
and that from time to time we can all see each other at family functions.
我爱你们如昔 父字
Anyway, I remain, your loving father.
万福玛利亚 满被圣宠者
Hail Mary, full of grace
女中尔为赞美
blessed art Thou amongst women
尔胎子耶稣并为赞美
and blessed is the fruit of Thy womb,Jesus.
天主圣母玛利亚
Holy Mary, mother of God
为我等罪人祈祷
pray for us sinners
全能天主降福这圣萨巴辛徽章
Almighty God, bless the insignia of Saint Sebastian the Martyr
愿徽章之神圣圣化受封人
that it may contribute to the sacredness of him to whom it is given.
麦克 你是否
Do you, Michael
发誓忠于徽章崇高的宗旨
promise to be faithful to the noble purposes of this order
赈济贫穷 扶救疾苦
to have a special care for the poor, the needy and those who are ill?
我承诺
I do so promise.
愿全能者天主圣父 圣子 圣神降福于你
May the blessing of Almighty God Father, Son, and Holy Spirit
与你同在以迨永远
descend upon you and remain with you forever.
阿们
Amen.
文森 名单上没有我们
Vincent, our name's not on the list.
那就写上去
Write it in.
曼西尼 M-A-N-I-N-I
Mancini. M-A-N-C-l-N-I.
有问题吗
Is there a problem here?
没有 名单上没有我的名字
No problem, our name's not on the list. My name's not on the list.
那请你马上离开 没有第二条路
Then you have to leave immediately. No two ways about it.
想跳舞吗
You want to dance?
乔 这是阿森 没关系 他们是客人
Joe, it's Vinnie. It's okay. These are our guests.
- 对不起 大卫 - 没关系
- I'm sorry, Dave. - It's all right.
阿森 欢迎光临
Vinnie, welcome to the party.
见到你真高兴
Good to see you.
我也是 这是我丈夫
It's good to see you again. This is my husband.
这是我儿子安东尼
This is my son, Anthony.
圣萨巴辛勳章在教廷
The order of Saint Sebastian is one of the highest honors
是颁给凡人的最高荣誉
the Catholic Church can bestow upon a layman.
它始于教皇格里哥利
The award was first granted by Pope Gregory
柯里昂先生与赌场的关系怎么办
What about Mr. Corleone's connections with Las Vegas gambling?
报道中有些照片
Presskits have pictures of...
还有他和黑道的牵扯呢
What about his involvement with the underworld?
你少说废话
Cut the crap, huh?
教皇今天亲自
The pope, the Holy Father himself
赐福麦克柯里昂
has this very day blessed Michael Corleone.
难道你比教皇更懂
You think you know better than the pope?
- 文森 - 干嘛
- Vincent! - Yes?
她爱你
She loves you.
所以 我也爱你
Yeah? I love you, too!
文森 我记得你
Hi Vincent. I remember you.
记得我 在哪儿
You remember me? From where?
上次我们一起参加的派对
From the last time when we were at a party together
你以前去过俱乐部
Did you come down to the club?
不是 是个婚礼
No, it was a wedding.
婚礼
A wedding?
我八岁 你十五岁时
I was 8; and you were 15
十五岁时我女友一大票
Well I, I had a lot of girlfriends when I was 15.
八岁的女友
8 year olds?
尤其是八岁
Especially 8 year olds!
玛莉呢
Where's Mary?
哪位叫玛莉一声 不好意思 阁下
Would somebody please hail Mary. Excuse me your Excellency.
你还没给我问候吻呢 亲戚相见要相吻
You know? You haven't kissed me hello yet. Relatives always kiss.
我们是亲戚吗
Oh, now we're related?
我是你的小堂妹
I'm your little cousin.
你父亲是谁
Who's your father?
给你个提示 他是意大利人
I'll give you a hint: he's Italian.
玛莉
Mary!
玛莉 大家都在等你呢
Mary, we've been waiting for you.
记住声音要低 嗯
Remember, remember now, keep your voice low, right?
还有笑容 别忘了笑
And smile! Don't forget to smile.
柯氏基金会荣誉主席
The honorary chairman of the Vito Corleone Foundation
小女玛莉柯里昂
My daughter, Mary Corleone.
谢谢 我大概继承了我父亲爱演说的习惯
Thanks; I think I inherited my father's love for speech making
今天是这样的
But here it goes
柯氏基金会在世界各国济贫
The Vito Corleone Foundation helps the impoverished of every country
资助艺术发展医学研究
gives grants to artists, funds medical research
尤其是致力于建设西西里岛
and is particularly dedicated to the resurrection of Sicily.
基尔戴大主教
Archbishop Gilday
这是一亿美元
here is, $100,000,000
代表维多柯里昂
for the poor of Sicily
献给西西里贫民
in the name of Vito Corleone.
不要只花在一处上
Don't spend it all in one place!
玛莉 我真为你骄傲
Mary, I'm so proud of you.
麦克
Michael
你为西西里做出了伟大的贡献
you've done a wonderful thing for Sicily.
但愿钱用在有需要的人身上
Well, let's just hope the money gets to the people who need it.
阿们
Amen!
今天的重头戏
But the most important part
强尼方亭
Johnny Fontane!
谢谢
Thank you very much.
今天来这里我很高兴
I'm happy to be here with you.
让我们同庆麦克柯里昂受封
I'd like you to join me in honoring Commendatore Michael Corleone.
我还特别为我们的主人 我们的教父准备了礼物
And I have something special for our host and Godfather.
我要为他演唱他最喜爱的歌
I just happen to know his favorite song.
麦克 你上哪儿去
Michael, where you going?
这是你最喜欢的歌
It's your favorite song!
我想去厨房听汤尼班的唱片
Uh, I'm off here to the kitchen to hear some Tony Bennett records.
是你最喜欢的歌 "沙西亚所有"
It's your favorite song "Sausage" His Own.
是啊我正要去吃沙西亚三明治 一会儿就回来
That's right; a sausage sandwich! I'll be back.
你好啊凯
Hello Kay
恭喜了 麦克 这真是一个很大的荣耀
Well congratulations, Michael, that's really quite an honor.
就是贵了一点 是不是
It's a little expensive, wouldn't you say?
蛋糕
Cake?
不吃 谢谢
No thank you
- 久违了吧 - 嗯
- It's been a long time, hasn't it? - Uh huh. Yeah.
- 八年了 - 是啊
- Eight years. - Yeah.
你看上去 很不错
You look, wonderful.
儿子有事要告诉你
Your son has something he wants to talk to you about.
我是为他事来的
I came here for him.
当律师到底有什么不好
What's wrong with being a lawyer?
没有 只是他不喜欢
Nothing, except he doesn't want it.
他热爱音乐 想投身音乐
He loves music, he wants his life to be in music.
音乐很好 我也爱音乐
Well music is great. I love music.
但是他做事应该有始有终
But he should finish what he started.
安东尼
Anthony...
我要走自己的路
I'm going my own way.
你的路
Your own way?
- 唱歌为业 - 是的
- Professional singer? - That's right.
那万一…万一失败了呢
And what happens what happens if you fail?
我不会失败的
I won't fail.
人总是自以为是
Men always believe that.
我知道
I know.
如果你有个法律学位 你的人生就等于上了双保险
If you have a Law degree, you're taking out insurance.
到时候你可以随心所欲
After that you can do whatever you want.
- 你可以为我做事 - 我决不会为你做事
- You can work for me... - I will never work for you.
我已经有很多不好的回忆了
I have bad memories.
每个家庭都会有些不愉快的回忆
Every family has bad memories.
我永远是你的儿子
I will always be your son.
但是绝不会沾手你的事业
But I will never have anything to do with your business.
安东尼 完成法律学位课程
Anthony, finish the Law degree.
不要
No.
这句"不要"可是得自于你
Well, that he got from you. That "no."
凯 你刚才应该帮我说服他
You could have helped me to convince him, Kay.
是吗 说服他干什么
Oh, convince him of what?
干什么
Of what?
他糟蹋了自己的人生
He throws his life away.
他抛弃了自己将有的伟业
He throws greatness away.
这叫做伟业
This is greatness?
麦克 你知道吗 你现在那么受人尊敬
You know Michael, now that you're so respectable
我反而觉得你更加可怕
I think you're more dangerous than you ever were.
其实我反而更喜欢还是普通帮派分子时的你
In fact, I preferred you when you were just a common Mafia hood.
- 好了 讲讲道理好不好 - 好
- Kay, now can we talk common sense here? - All right.
好
Okay.
安东尼知道是你杀了弗雷多
Tony knows that you killed Fredo.
你来这里到底是为了什么
What did you come here for?
来保护我儿子
I came here to protect my son.
我不是来看教廷褒扬你
I didn't come here to see you disguised by your church.
在我看来这场典礼很可耻
I think that was a shameful ceremony.
我一辈子都在保护我的儿子
I spent my life protecting my son.
在保护我的家庭
I spent my life protecting my FAMILY!
你讲讲道理好吗
Let's be reasonable, Okay?
你不是最讲道理的吗
That's your big thing, isn't it, Michael?
用杀人 来建立的道理
Reason. Backed up by murder.
天啊你恨我 你恨我
Oh God, You hate me, you hate me.
不
No
我不恨你
I don't hate you.
我怕你
I dread you.
凯 我尽我所能来保护你们
I did what I could,  Kay, to protect all of you
不受世上的恐怖威胁
from the horrors of this world.
你却成为了我的恐惧
But you became my horror.
可子孩子们依然爱你 尤其是玛莉
The children still love you though. Especially Mary.
这一点很重要 我们可以从这一点上下手
That's something. We can build on that
为了他们
For their sake.
我们试试吧
Let's try.
除非你让安东尼走自己的路
Only if you let Tony go free to have his own life.
远离你
Away from you.
我让安东尼走
I'll let Tony go.
谢谢你
Thank you.
你那鞋都能用来做武器了
You could hurt somebody with those.
你也辛苦了大半天 我带你四处看看吧
You've been working too hard, let me show you around.
你能不能帮我安排采访麦克柯里昂
Can you get me an interview with Michael Corleone?
不行 虽然我是他的亲属也帮不上忙
Uh, no. I'm a relative but I can't do that.
还有其他可以为你效劳的吗
What else can I do for you?
绣花枕头一个
Handsome but useless.
是吗
Oh yeah?
不要紧 我愿意赌一赌
That's okay. I'll gamble.
喜欢赌 那我们去亚特兰大城吧
You like to gamble? Why don't we go to Atlantic City
那是我的地盘 我来带你见识见识怎么赌一把
My town. I'll show you how to gamble.
好啊不过我只喜欢赢 你怎么知道哪一把能赢
Yeah, but I like to win. How will I know what numbers to pick?
你看我像个输家吗
Do I look okay like a guy who's gonna lose?
那个人一脸凶相吓人
Spooky looking guy there.
这种凶煞来柯家干什么
What is a guy like that doing at Michael Corleone's house?
那是乔札萨的狗腿子
That's Joey Zasa's bulldog.
你认得他
You know that guy?
是 我认得
Yeah I know that guy.
他叫安东尼史基拉罗
That guy's name is Anthony Squigliaro.
浑号"蚂蚁"
They call him The Ant.
他的子弹上都涂有氰化毒
He dips his bullets in Cyanide.
艾图贝洛阁下
Don Altobello
我来表示敬意
I came to pay my respects
谢谢
Grazie.
你是我父亲的挚友
You honor my father's friendship.
我的教女在哪里
Where is my goddaughter?
想当年你还不过是我手里抱着的小娃娃
It was not so long ago I held you in these old hands
麦克
Michael
请坐
Piachere? Cominar
站着可以了
No, I stand; I stand
麦克 我已经老了 不再有年轻人的活力和愤怒了
Michael, I lost all the venom, all the juice of youth.
对女人也失去了欲望
I lost the lust for women
现在我的头脑很清楚
and now my mind is clear
知道自己对上主的职责
My duty to God is clear
有件特别的事我想要你帮忙
I have a special favor to ask
能不能让我加入柯氏基金会
Can I attach my name to the Vito Corleone Foundation
以使你我能更全面地融合一体
so that you and I can be joined in name and spirit
一百万美金
One million dollars
教父
Godfather
你真善心
Don Altobello, you have such heart
走 我们去喝杯酒
Come; let's go and sample some of Italy vino.
梵蒂冈教廷对这些股东的背景全然不知
The Vatican knows nothing about these shareholders
好
Good
我一向杞人忧天
I have a tendency to worry
我担心太明显 会让人起疑
We've increased our position substantially and naturally I worry
别担心 我们签有合约
Stop worrying. We have an agreement.
那就好 我担心得头发也白了
Good. How do you think I got this grey hair?
- 柯里昂先生 耽误…两秒钟 - 法兰克 你好吗
- Mr. Corleone, two seconds - Frank, how are you?
谢谢你对游泳池建设的贡献
Thank you very much for your contribution to the Board's swimming pool.
另外我们希望你能支持华里士竞选法官
And we need your help on Sam Wallace's candidacy for judgeship.
- 一个好法官总是有用的 - 谢谢你
- We always can use a good judge. - Thank you
安德鲁
Andrew!
阁下 我的教子安德鲁哈金
Your Excellency, my Godson, Andrew Hagan
我的兄弟汤姆的大儿子
my brother Tom Hagan's eldest boy.
他在毕兰主教座下已有多年
He's been assistant to Bishop Greening for years now.
期望调任梵蒂冈
Hoping for an assignment to the Vatican.
年轻优秀的教士罗马随时欢迎
There's always a place in Rome for a fine young priest.
他的母亲 泰瑞莎 这是基尔戴大主教
His mother Theresa Hagen Archbishop Gilday
幸会
Honored to meet you.
柯先生 你好 我是葛莉丝汉摩顿
Mr. Corleone. Hi, Grace Hamilton.
文森曼西尼对我说会向你提起我
Vincent Mancini promised that he'd tell you about me.
说也许你会见我
that maybe you'd see me.
- 文森曼西尼可有提到她 - 没有
- Vincent Mancini called about her? - No
葛莉丝你答应我不乱跑的
Grace, you promised me you'd stay up there.
- 我知道 - 两次了
- I know. - Twice.
札萨来了
Joey Zasa showed up.
我让他在外厅等
We've got him waiting in the lobby.
他说要亲自向你道贺…致敬
Says he wants to personally congratulate you and show his respect.
我非得见他
Do I have to see him?
他说你是他的老大
He says you're his patrone.
而且只要求一分钟
and he only wants a minute.
文森 你最喜欢哪个姑姑
Hey Vinnie! Who's your favorite Aunt?
你
You are.
今天我会跟麦克提你的事情
Today I'm gonna talk to Michael about your little problem.
你该早告诉我
I wish you would have warned me Conn'
我也好穿得光鲜一点
I could have worn a better suit.
米乌奇协会选你
The Meucci Association has elected you
为今年度意裔楷模
their Italian-American Man of the Year.
米乌奇
Meucci
米乌奇是谁
Who's Meucci?
意裔美籍他发明电话
He's the Italian-American who invented the telephone.
比贝尔早了一年
He did it one year before Alexander Graham Bell.
挑今天来只为这档子事
And this is the reason you've come to my home on this day.
去把鱼喂了
Go feed the fish.
有件事情让我很不痛快
I got a stone in my shoe, Mr. Corleone.
有个替我跑腿的小瘪三
A two-bit punk who works for me
他自命是你的亲属
The one who, thinks he's related to you.
小混蛋
A bastard.
他在这里
He's here.
文森曼西尼 他在宴会上
Vincent Mancini. He's at the party.
带他进来
Well bring him in.
我们谈就好了
I think it's good we talk.
不用 谢谢
No thanks.
我有个有麻烦
I have a problem
我要弄清楚这到底是我的
and I want to find out if it is my problem
还是你的麻烦
or your problem
乔 你做你的买卖
Joe, your business is your business.
我不沾利益也不分红
I have no interests or percentage.
我是局外人
I'm out
很好
Good.
那么就是我的麻烦了
Then it's my problem.
麦克 你认得文森
Michael, you know Vincent Mancini
大哥的遗孤
Sonny's boy.
柯里昂先生 你好吗
How you doin' Mr. Corleone?
你好吗
How you doing?
很好 你好吗
I'm doin' good. How you doin'?
- 很好 - 好一场盛宴
- Good. - Good party.
你喜欢
Oh you like it?
是 我溜进来的
Yeah, I had to sneak in.
至少你盛装前来
Well, you're dressed for it.
你和札萨先生有什么过节吗
So, what's the trouble between you and Mr. Joe Zasa?
小麻烦 我会摆平
There's trouble. I'll take care of it.
你这样非常愚蠢
That's foolish of you.
我愚蠢
Foolish of ME?
这家伙才愚蠢 对不对
It's a little foolish of this guy. Don't you think?
对不对 对不对
Right? RIGHT?
脾气火爆还真像他爸
Temper like his father.
文森 目前札萨先生拥有…
Vincent. Mr. Joe Zasa now owns
昔日柯里昂家在纽约的生意
what used to be the Corleone family business, in New York.
他好意把你安插在他帮中
Out of the kindness of his heart he gave you a job in his family.
你不听我劝硬要接受
Contrary to my advice, you took the job.
我给你提供一了个更好的合法工作
I'd offered you something, better, in the legitimate world.
你回绝了
You turned me down.
现在你们结了怨便来找我
Now, you both come to me with this bad blood.
你还指望我怎么做
And what do you expect me to do?
难道我是个流氓头吗
Am I a gangster?
不是 你不是流氓头
No, you're not a gangster.
爸爸的以前的老邻里都被搞得乌烟瘴气
That's was Papa's neighborhood, now it's a sewer.
札萨根本没有用心在打理
Zasa runs it like a disgrace that's what the women tell me.
康妮 那是旧事
That's the past Connie.
我靠自己的本事赚得那块地盘
I earned that territory with my talent.
帮会分配给我 你也同意
Commission gave it to me, and you approved.
是的
Yes.
麦克叔
Uncle Michael
我来赴宴不是求援
I came to the party here I'm not here to ask for any kind of help
我完全杀的了这混帐
I could just kill this bastard
需要帮助的是他
He's the one who needs the help.
那杀了他啊
So kill him
你们的事和我有什么关系
What has all this have to do with me?
背着你他经常骂
Well, he's going around behind your back saying
"去他妈的麦克柯里昂"
fuck Michael Corleone all time.
这跟你相干了吧
That's it, see, that's one thing it has to do with you
当他的面骂一次 当他的面骂一次啊！
Say it to his face, one time. Say it to his face, one time!
柯里昂先生 混蛋都撒谎
Mr. Corleone, all bastards are liars.
莎士比亚的诗句中都这么写
Shakespeare wrote poems about it.
麦克叔 我该怎么处置他
What am I gonna do with this guy, Uncle Michael?
怎么处置他
WHAT AM I GONNA DO WITH THIS GUY?
乔
Joey
如有人在市里到处跑
If there's some guy running around this city
还骂"妈的麦克柯里昂"
saying "fuck Michael Corleone"
这种杂碎我们怎么处置
what do we do, with a piece of shit like that?
把他当狗东西 不是吗
He's a fucking dog. No?
对 说这种话的人
Yes it's true. If anyone would say such a thing
肯定不是朋友
they would not be a friend.
就是个狗东西
They would be a dog.
我同札萨先生没有利害冲突
My interests don't conflict with Mr. Joe Zasa's
你只是还不知道
Oh you don't know how much
你跟他大有冲突
your interests conflict with Mr. Joe Zasa's, Uncle Michael.
文森
Vinnie
麦克 支持他
He needs your support, Michael.
别让我再做他手下了
Don't let me word for this guy no more Uncle Michael.
让我来帮你
let me come work for you.
- 替我做事 - 是的
- For me? - Yeah.
做什么 当打手
As what? Tough guy?
我用不着打手 律师倒多多益善
I don't need tough guys. I need more lawyers.
既然无怨无债
Since we have no conflicts, no debts
我接受馈赠并祝你如意
I accept your tribute. I wish you well.
文森 同札萨先生和好 来
Vincent, Make your peace with Mr. Joe Zasa. C'mon
好 去啊
Okay. Go on.
小混蛋
Bastardo.
文森
Vincent
天啊 快停下来 你疯了
For Christ's sakes, stop! What's the matter with you?
把他弄走
Get him out of here.
我的天
Oh,Jesus.
麦克叔 我跟姑姑说过现在还不是时候
Uncle Michael, I told Connie it wasn't the right time for this.
关门
Close it.
我知道你现在转入金融证券界
I know you're into banks and Wall Street
但帮里事务仍由你作主
But everyone knows you're the final word, like the Supreme Court.
我要保护你 你的律师办不到
I want to protect you from these guys. Your lawyers can't do that.
- 你办得到 - 是 我办得到
- And you can? - Yeah, I can do that.
我何必怕札萨
And why should I be afraid of Joe Zasa?
他知道你妨碍他
Well, he knows you're stopping him
在帮里往上爬
from rising up in the commission, Uncle Mike
要我说就杀了他 你下令我摆平
I say we make him dead. You give me the order, I'll take care of it.
- 你来摆平 - 是的
- You'll take care of it? - Yeah.
也许你应该跟随我几周
Maybe you should come with me for a few weeks
观察观察
See what happens.
好的
Okay.
看你学到多少
See if you learn
然后再商量你的前途
And, umm, we'll talk about your future.
我不会令你失望的
I won't let you down.
快准备好了
We're just about ready.
情形如何
So what happened?
如何
What happened?
跟札萨共处一室会如何
They put me in a room with Joey Zasa. what's gonna happen?
我咬掉了他的耳朵
I bit the guy's ear off.
好 大家看着牌子…
Here we go. Watch the card.
等一下
Hold it
- 文森 - 有
- Vincent - Yeah
跟我们合照 来
Take the picture with us. Come on.
外套不错
Nice jacket.
往中央靠拢 先生
Closer to the center, if you would, sir.
谢谢 要照了
And here we go.
预备
Ready
笑
Smile.
好极了
Excellent.
星期一的时候我会把照片送来
I'll have it for you on Monday.
奶油蛋糕 漂亮
Butter cake. Beautiful.
教父 安索特为贵家族烘制
Godfather, this is the cake for you and your family from Enzo the baker.
谢谢
Grazie.
你要切吗
You want to do it? All right.
来吧
You lead
文森
Vincent
什么事 亲爱的
What do you want, sweetheart?
你爱不爱我
Do you love me?
好了 睡觉吧
Come on. Go to bed.
- 说吧 - 好了 睡觉
- Come on. Say it. - Go to bed.
- 你说 - 我爱你 我爱你
- No. Say it. - I love you. I love you.
我也爱你
I love you too.
你养了猫
You got a cat?
帮我倒杯水好吗 我渴了
Go get us some water, would you? I'm thirsty.
快去 去吧
C'mon, c'mon
我想我终于明白自己的地位了
Well, I just guess I know my place.
我竟然甘心听他使唤
I can't believe I'm actually getting up to do this.
倒杯水 做蛋糕
Get me a glass of water, bake me a cake.
请字都没有
Whatever happened to "please"?
好小子 快来 我们去散个步
C'mon! Good boy, sock-face. Let's go for a walk.
快放了她
Hey. C'mon, let her go.
快割她的喉咙
Cut her fucking throat, man
你说什么
What'd you say?
我说快割开她的喉咙
I said cut her fucking throat.
快放了她
Okay, chief, let her go.
扔掉你的枪 否则就割开她喉咙
Drop your gun man, or he's gonna cut her throat.
你他妈疯了 我不认识她
What are fucking crazy, I hardly know this broad.
你割吧 我在乎什么
Go ahead, cut her, what the fuck do I care?
由不得你 这妞死定了
You got no choice man, the chick's gonna be dead.
你敢伤害她 我会杀了你们两个
You hurt her and I'll kill you both.
你放下匕首我放你走
You give up that knife, I'll let you go.
杀了她 快点
You cut her throat man, RIGHT NOW!
等一下
HEY!
接下来我会用行动说服你 可别吓坏了
I'm gonna do something to convince you. Don't get frightened.
别作突然的动作 看着我
Don't do any sudden movements, just watch me, all right?
- 听见没有 - 有
- You hear what I said? - Yeah.
好
Okay.
妈的
Oh, shit!
把刀子放下 放下
Drop the knife, g'head, DROP IT!
好孩子 坐下 我有话说
Good boy. Sit down I wanna talk to you.
这才聪明 坐下 我有话说
That was a wise choice, sit down. I wanna talk to you.
取下面罩
Lose the mask.
放轻松 抽不抽烟
Relax, have a smoke, you smoke?
这是谁的主意
Whose idea was this?
谁指使你来 快说
Who sent you? C'mon tell me, who sent you?
没人指使
No one.
你仔细看过这家伙没
Take a good look at this guy?
是
Yeah.
谁指使你来
So who sent you?
乔…札萨
It was Joey, Joey Zasa.
饶命
No!
你没事吧
You Okay?
你刚才任他们杀我
You were gonna let them kill me!
没有 我不会让你收到任何伤害
No, I wasn't gonna let anything happen to you.
猪 你可恶
You pig! You sick fuck!
你不是要赌吗
C'mon sweetheart, that's gambling.
那就是赌命
You wanted gambling, that's gambling.
报警吧
Call the police.
另一个你也杀了
You killed the other guy, too?
他要夺我的枪 自卫杀人
Went for my gun. Self defense, justifiable homicide.
快报警
Go ahead, call the police.
你上哪去 不行 不准拍照
Where you goin'? Oh no, no, no. No pictures.
我要拍照
I'm gonna take some pictures first.
不要
No.
你有枪
You had a gun.
他们只有刀
They only had a knife.
你可以制伏他们
You could have talked them into surrendering;
报警处理
handed them over to the police.
札萨派他们来 我只是回敬他一下
Zasa sent these guys, I just sent him a message. That's all.
现在他又得回敬你
Now he has to send you a message back.
乔札萨要回敬我
Joey Zasa's gonna send ME a message back?
他还想回敬我
Joey Zasa's gonna send ME a message back.
他没做错 他问出了札萨的名字
He did the right thing, he got Zasa's name.
这跟札萨不相干
What has Joey Zasa got to with anything
- 他是个疯子 - 札萨
- Joey Zasa's a potzle. - Joey Zasa.
算了 你是本性难移
All right, you are what you are. It's your nature.
你跟着我 不许妄动
You stay close to me. You don't do anything.
嘴巴闭紧眼睛睁大
You keep your mouth shut, and your eyes open.
- 听我吩咐 懂不懂 - 我懂
- And you do what I tell you. Understand? - Understand.
- 我与帮会之间有点问题 - 我知道
- I got problems with the Commission, young man. - I know thar.
你现在是越帮越忙
Yes. You don't make them easier.
我知道 我本来无意杀人一时手快
I understand that, it wasn't my idea that this happened, you know?
好了 你下去吧
All right. Go on, get out of here.
麦克
Michael
什么
Yes?
现在他们怕你了
Now they'll fear you.
也许他们应该怕你
Maybe they should fear you.
抱歉 什么事
B.J., excuse me. what's up?
麦克 大主教电话
Michael, the Archbishop just called back.
他对你的出价做了出色的安排
He's arranged some amazing things for your bidding.
宣传排山倒海的 你成了大善慈家
Publicity is phenomenal. You're the new Rockefeller of philanthropy.
请在这里签名
Sign right here please.
时代不同了
Times do change, don't they?
我父亲不喜欢基金会
My father hated foundations.
他喜欢亲力亲为
He loved doing it by himself.
同样为人 但我们有很大的不同
Man to man. But we, we're different, huh?
我们跟那些大企业没啥不同
It's no different than any large corporation.
本小利大
We control a lot of money with very little.
少付税又不受政府控制
Minimize taxes, with, no government control.
什么事
Yes?
好
Right.
教父
Godfather.
安德鲁
Andrew.
教父 我要起程到罗马去了
Godfather. Off to Rome.
我要感激你所做的一切
I wanted to thank you for all you've done for me.
- 一起用餐吧 - 不用了 谢谢
- C'mon, you want to have some breakfast with us? - No thanks I can't.
你的意大利语行吗
All right. How's your Italian?
- 他父亲是个名律师 - 我知道
- His father was a great lawyer. - I know.
生前却看不到他被授命为牧师 我却有幸看到
Didn't live to see him ordained. I did.
见过那种场面吗
You ever seen one of those?
真不错 我以你为傲
Oh, beautiful. I was so proud.
安德鲁 你从梵蒂冈听到什么风声
Andrew, if you hear any rumors flying around the Vatican
- 要让我知道 - 不 安德鲁是认真虔诚的
- you let me know, all right? - Oh no, no. Andrew has the true faith.
柯里昂阁下 请帮帮我
Don Corleone. I need your help.
不是点蜡烛的小事
And not just to light a little candle.
我擅长为教廷
My, gift, was to be able to persuade people
劝募献金
to give, to the Holy Church.
罗马令我掌管梵蒂冈银行
Then, Rome decides, to put me in charge of the Vatican bank.
但我不是理财的料子
But I was never a true banker.
只怪我太相信朋友
Msisa culpa, I trusted my friends.
友谊与金钱
Friendship and money
- 有若油与水 - 说得对
- oil and water - Indeed.
然而这些朋友
But these, friends
利用教廷之名饱其贪念
Use the good name of the Church, to feed their greed.
赔了钱
If money was lost
被责难的只会是我
Then I am to blame.
但愿祷告能
Oh, if only prayer could
补足七亿赤字
pay off our seven-hundred million dollar deficit.
七亿六千九百万元
Seven-hundred and sixty-nine million.
"屹立公司"股份…
The Church owns 25%
教廷拥有25%
of a large corporation, Immobiliare
你知道我说的
You know the one I mean.
世界第一大地主
Largest landlord on earth
房地遍布全球 总值六十亿元
real estate all over the world worth six billion dollars.
的确是
That's true.
要控制该公司
And the Vatican vote is necessary
必须有梵蒂冈的一票
for control.
不对 你弄错了
No. No, no. You're mistaken.
此事非一人能决定
This isn't a question of one person deciding
不是一票能决定
one deciding vote.
"屹立"与其他公司一样
This is like any other company in the world.
有董监事 有规章
We have directors, we have rules.
古老保守的规章
We have very old rules.
须得教皇亲自批准
The Pope himself, would have to approve you.
我们已出售赌场
We've sold the casinos
以及相关的生意
all businesses having to do with gambling.
我们对不法的生意
We have no interests, or investments
既无兴趣亦全无瓜葛
in anything illegitimate.
柯氏准备将五亿美元
The Corleone's prepared to deposit 500 million dollars
存入梵蒂冈银行…
in the Vatican bank
只等柯里昂先生
at such time as Mr. Corleone receives
掌握"屹立"的多数控制
majority control of Immobiliare.
"屹立"可有新面貌
Immobiliare could be something new
成为欧洲集团
a European conglomerate.
少数家族控制这种公司
Few families, have control of such a company.
今日世界…
It seems in today's world
免除债务
the power to absolve debt is greater than
似乎强过宽恕之心
the power of forgiveness
六亿美元
Six hundred million dollars.
不要高估宽恕之心
Don't overestimate the power of forgiveness.
柯里昂阁下
Don Corleone
"屹立"这笔交易
this deal with Immobiliare can
能使你跻身世界级富翁
make you one of the richest men in the world.
你和贵家族的历史旧事
Your whole past history and the history of your family
将因此洗净
will be washed away.
六亿美元
600 million.
动议讨论事项
The motion and a discussion
关鱼柯氏集团所提议
relates to Corleone Group's proposal
由该集团取得一亿新发A级表决权股票
to acquire 100 million newly issued class "A' ' voting shares.
柯氏资金直接投入"屹立"
Corleone's capital invested directly into International lmmobiliare
名重当世的欧洲公司
an old and respected European company.
不过麦克柯里昂野心勃勃
But Michael Corleone has an ambitious program
欲将该房地产公司
to expand this real estate holding company
国际化
into an international conglomerate
接收"屹立"有迹可寻 股票飙涨
Immobiliare Takeover Appears Likely. Stock Soars
而是东方有效率的方法
but by Eastern techniques of efficiency
集中力量
and focus
柯里昂先生
Mr. Corleone
请问最近你是否将两亿元…
Isn't it true that you recently
存入梵蒂冈银行
deposited $200 million in the Vatican Bank
该银行为"屹立"的关系企业
which is affiliated with International Immobiliare?
确有此事 不行吗
This is true. Why not?
存款时机
Wasn't there any questioning about
是否有蹊跷
the timing on this particular deposit
存款之事据说
or wasn't there some talk about
主席 容我发言
Mr. Chairman, if I may?
柯氏基金会
The Vito Andolino Corleone Foundation
由柯里昂先生之千金玛莉 任董事长
of which Mr. Corleone's daughter Mary is chairman
以一亿元成立该基金会
has established an endowment in the amount of one hundred million dollars
柯里昂家族提供基金
The money comes from his own family
将由梵蒂冈管理
and will be administered by the Vatican.
解答疑问了吧
Answer your question?
我一向深信助人为最有利的事
I have always believed helping your fellow man
利人利己
is profitable in every sense, personally and bottom-line.
各位股东同仁
My fellow shareholders
假如欧美能学习合作
if Europe and America can learn to cooperate
汇集资金分享彼此的市场
if we can learn to pool our wealth, share our markets
即能所向无敌
we can defeat any competition
举世无匹
anywhere in the world.
拨冗赴会谨此致谢
Let me thank you for the time you've given me today
希望各位能赞同本人所提 谢谢
and I hope that you will look favorably on my proposal. Thank you.
对不起 容我说句话
Listen, let me at this microphone here.
我们怎么能让这样一个罪犯掌管公司
How can we let a criminal like thar run our company?
他一脸西西里匪相 你们看不到吗
He's got the map of Sicily on his face. Can't you see it?
秩序 秩序
Order! Order!
他不是天主教徒就是个帮派分子
He's either Catholic or mafioso.
汉摩顿投资集团不支持这项提案
The Hamilton Investors Group cannot support this proposal.
大主教阁下
Your Excellency?
主席
Mr. Chairman
梵蒂冈银行认为
the Vatican Bank feels
屹立国际公司
that International Immobiliare
由柯里昂先生掌理可以安心
will be safe in Mr. Corleone's hands.
至于审核定夺事宜
Subject to audit and final ratification
权利在罗马教廷
which must take place in Rome
请与本席一同欢迎柯里昂先生
please join me in welcoming Mr. Michael Corleone
爸
Dad
安东尼告诉我有关基金会的事
Tony says that I'm a front for the foundation
说你利用我来做门面
that you're using me just to pull the strings
获得自己想要的利益
to get the money where you want it.
请别这么说
Come on. Please.
提升个人形象
To shine up your public image
玛莉
Mary
这个基金是为了它现在的宗旨而建立的
this is real, this foundation
这是真的
It's real.
我之前想要安东尼加入
I wanted Anthony to be a part of it.
你们两个可以同心协力
I thought you two would be together on this.
我不会干涉你
I won't interfere.
除非你来向我求助
I'll help only if you ask.
但这些到底是为了什么
But what is this really for?
你这么做是为了什么
Why are you doing this?
而我又是为了什么
Why am I doing this?
我这么做是为了我的孩子们
I'm doing this for my children.
你也是为你的孩子们
You're doing it for your children too.
但这基金会应该帮助所有人
This foundation is supposed to help all people.
当然 这是宗旨
Of course. That's the purpose.
这是合法的 玛莉
This is legitimate, Mary.
我保证这是合法的
I swear this is legitimate.
爸 我希望这件事令我们更加亲密
Dad, I want this to bring me closer to you.
我会不惜一切
I would burn in hell
保护你的安全
to keep you safe.
不要 你乘那辆 我跟麦克一道走
No, no. You go in the other car. I'll ride with Michael.
我与你家交情最深
As your family's oldest friend
一向由我给你通风报信
I'm always chosen to bring you messages.
艾图贝洛阁下 请说
Tell me, Don Altobello.
你以前给那些老伙计赚的钱 他们很感激
Your old partners are grateful for the money you made them.
可以说他们都崇拜你
They worship you.
但现在你抛弃了他们 这让他们很伤心
But their hearts are broken because they think you abandoned them.
"屹立"的生意 他们也要入股
They want to share your deal on Immobiliare
大家还是一家人
to be a family again.
也能帮他们洗钱
It can purify their money.
这件事我办不到
This I cannot do.
"屹立"必须是桩合法生意
Immobiliare must be legitimate.
我明白 可是他们不高兴
I know. But they're unhappy.
你呢
And you?
我自己别无所求
I ask nothing for myself.
只盼着能怡养天年
Only peace in my old age.
可是我得抚慰身边的人
But I must please the world around me.
麦克 你爸通情达理
Michael, your father was a reasonable man.
学学他吧
Learn from him.
我从父亲那里学到许多
I learned many things from my father.
大家见个面吧 老伙计
Call a meeting, my friend
借此来解决我们的恩怨
so there are no debts or grudges.
我们会解决所有的问题
We will make the peace
你和我一起
you and I.
罗马 梵蒂冈
今天梵蒂冈宣称
The Vatican announced today
教皇保禄六世已因病
that Pope Paul VI has canceled his Sunday blessing
取消周日祈福
due to ill health.
医生要求卧床静养
His physician has ordered total bed rest
同时停止一切活动
and cessation of all activities.
刚刚举行了记者会
They just had a press conference.
宣布教皇病重
They said the pope's condition is grave. gravissimo, they said.
本次会议的目的在于批准
The purpose of this meeting is to ratify
纽约各股东通过的动议
the motion passed by our shareholders in New York.
稍等
Please
本集团代表天主教友财团
our group represents a consortium of Catholic businessmen
反对柯氏掌权
against the Corleone control.
梵蒂冈已经投赞成票
The Vatican has cast its vote.
柯氏集团也已控制了董事会
The Corleone Group already controls the board.
但根据拉特兰之约
According to the Lateran Treaty
梵蒂冈投的票必须在罗马
the Vatican's vote must be ratified
由教皇亲自批准
here in Rome by the pope.
教皇病重
The pope is gravely ill.
在他康复之前
Until he recovers
我无能为力
I am powerless.
那万一他一病不起呢
What if he dies?
那么套句美国俗话
Then as you Americans say
过往一切一笔勾消
All bets are off.
各位 等一下
Gentlemen, please.
这只是个短暂耽搁 仅此而已
This is a brief delay, nothing more.
大主教 各位先生
Your Excellency, gentlemen.
请大家一起祷告
I advise you join us in our prayers
祈求教皇早日康复
for the Holy Father's recovery.
我们早就说好了
We had an agreement
这场会议只是形式罢了 只是个形式
This meeting was to be merely a formality. That's all it was.
- 请坐下 - 我宁可站着 谁能回答我
- Please sit down. - I'd rather stand. Could someone answer?
是我们把自己逼到了这里
We have put ourselves on the line
"屹立"在欧洲根深蒂固
The Immobiliare has its roots in the European tradition.
各位务必要了解
Please try to understand.
我了解
I understand.
我了解你们的卑鄙手段
Your tactics are despicable.
这话从柯里昂先生口中说出来 可真是个不小的罪名
Well, that's quite an indictment, coming from a Corleone.
各位
Gentlemen
请别忘了你们现在是在梵蒂冈
Remember you're in the Vatican. Please.
你们到底 想要什么
What is it that you want?
你可以取得控制权
Yes. You will take control.
我们非常推举你为船队掌舵
We'll gladly put you at the helm of our little fleet
但所有船只的方向必须一致
but our ships must all sail in the same direction.
否则
Otherwise
谁知道你能在我们的船上呆多久
who can say how long your stay with us will last?
这并不是针对你
It's not personal.
这是生意场你了解的 教父
It's only business. You should know, Godfather.
当然
Very well.
你们要跟我做生意
You want to do business with me
那我就跟你们做生意
I will do business with you.
他们全是毒蛇
Vipers, all of them.
一群披着宗教外衣的伪善者
We're back with the Borgias.
- 麦克叔 - 安德鲁
- Uncle Michael. - Andrew.
我听说你来了 能在这里见到你太好了
I heard you were here. It's so nice to see you.
- 文森 - 安德鲁 你好吗
- Vincent. - Andrew, how are you?
包家怎么了 他们的时代早就结束了
What is this with the Borgias? Those days are over, Michael.
认得吗
Recognize it?
嗯
Yeah.
仁科橄榄油
Genco Olive Oil.
我们的祖父就是从这里开始的
That's where our grandfather got his start.
每周靠送货赚3美元
as a delivery boy making three bucks a week.
三年后他拥有了这家公司
Three years later, he owned the company.
美国才有这种事
Only in America.
没错
That's it.
文森 你最近躲到哪儿去了
Vincenzo, where have you been hiding?
要你帮忙的时候
You deserted us
扔下我们不管
when we need your help so badly.
现在我回来了 要我做什么
Well now I'm back, what can I do for you?
除掉札萨
Get rid of Joe Zasa.
他卖毒品给孩子们
He sells drugs to children.
我年轻的时候还太平无事
When I was a girl, it was different.
如今老了反而不敢走夜路
I'm an older woman, I'm afraid to walk the streets at night.
他们大概在哪里
Where are they supposed to be at?
路易 怎么回事
Lou, what's going on?
我们已经迟了
We're late.
我什么时候让你失望过
Have I ever let you down?
我相信你
I trust you.
不要担心
Don't worry about it.
太谢谢你了
Thank you very much.
祝你们愉快
Enjoy yourself.
这是怎么回事
What was that?
我的邻居有些麻烦
Neighborhood's in trouble.
你一直都这么照应你的邻居
You're keeping your eye out for them?
不错
That's right.
我呢
And for me?
从今以后都照应你
From now on.
我一直都在想念你
I missed you all this time.
我也想念你 小妹妹
I missed you, too, cousin.
我很怀念以前大家一起成长的时光
I missed growing up with all my cousins.
没认识你之前我就想念你了
I didn't know you, and I missed you.
你还记得当年我们父亲的事吗
Do you remember stories about our fathers, the old days?
记得 你想知道些什么
Yeah. What do you want to know?
山尼大伯是怎么样的人
What was Sonny like?
他是城里的风头人物
He was the prince of the city.
他在我出生之前就死了
He died before I was born
但我听过关于他的许多故事 他是个传奇
But I heard a million stories. He was a legend.
那我爸爸呢
What about my father?
他是个伟大的人物
A great man, your father.
他是个英雄 他拯救了整个家族
He's a hero. He saved the family.
- 文森 - 什么
- Vincent. - What?
他有没有杀自己的亲兄弟
Did he kill his own brother?
没有
No.
所以那些传言都是谎话
So those are all lies?
只是传言 知道吗
Just stories, sweetheart. OK?
知道了
OK.
我相信你
I believe you.
我很高兴你在我身边
I'm glad you're around.
我也很高兴
I'm glad you're here too.
堂哥
Cousin.
我真想把札萨也带上来 然后把他推下去
I'd like to take Joey Zasa up for a ride in this and drop him.
札萨算什么
Joey Zasa is nothing.
不过是个微不足道的小跑腿
He's a small-time enforcer.
也就吹吹牛 吓唬吓唬人 没什么
He bluffs, threats, but nothing.
老远你就能知道他来了
You'll be able to see him coming a mile away.
- 我们应该趁早杀了他以免 - 不行
- We should kill him before he kills... - No!
永远不要恨你的敌人 这会影响你的判断
Never hate your enemies. It affects your judgment.
新泽西 亚特兰大城
晚上好 柯里昂先生 很高兴再次见到你
Good evening. Nice to see you again, Mr. Corleone.
我们相信你 让你来掌管我们赌场的钱
We trusted you to manage our money in the casinos.
可还不到二十年 你就卖掉赌场
It's not even 20 years you sold the casinos
帮我们大家都大赚了一笔
and you made fortunes for all of us.
厉害啊柯里昂阁下
Bravo, Don Corleone!
过奖
Thank you.
朋友们 我到这里来
Friends, I have come here
是因为我们的共同事业已经结束了
because, our business together is done.
我们都赚了大钱
We have prospered
现在是时候
and now it is time for us
解除我们之间的合作关系了
to dissolve the business relationship between us.
到此为止
That's it.
不过我有份小礼物
But I do have a little surprise
各位在赌场所持的股份
Your shares in the casino
我会免去所有程序
I thought I'd cut through all the red tape
直接兑现
so you can get your money right away.
五千万
$50 million!
每个人都不一样 按当初
Not everybody gets the same. It depends on how much...
- 没你的份儿 - 你资的额度及时间长短
- Nothing for you. - you invested and how long for.
麦克 你真大方
Michael, this is really generous!
好极了
Oh, wonderful.
谢谢
Grazier
巴利西 你当初投了多少
Hey, Parisi, how much did you invest?
记不得了
I don't remember.
上帝会保佑你的 麦克
Michael, you're blessed.
我的家族担了大部分苦差事
My family has done much of the hard work
冒了很多风险
taken many risks
来为你们赚钱
all to make money for the rest of the families.
各位都认识乔札萨
You all know Joey Zasa.
我承认他是个大人物
He is, I admit, an important man.
时代周刊封面登过他的照片
His picture is on the cover of the New York Times Magazine.
绅士杂志还封他为最佳着装帮派人物
He gets the Esquire magazine award for the best-dressed gangster.
各大报纸赞扬他 因为他雇用黑人
The newspapers praise him because he hires blacks into his family
表现得那么宽厚
which shows he has a good heart
他是个名人 天知道
He is famous. Who knows?
也许有一天
Maybe one day
他会让在做各位都成为名人
he will make all of you popular.
不错
It's true.
我讲究穿着和仪容
I make more of a bella figura.
这是我的天性
That is my nature.
但我也想让自己的事业合法化
But I also want to make a move into legitimate enterprises.
想要教皇给我封勋
I'd like to get a little pin from the pope.
不错 我雇佣黑人
Sure, I take the blacks
甚至是南美籍人
and the Spanish into my family
因为这里是美国
because that's America.
你敢担保他们不在我们的地盘上贩毒
And you guarantee that they don't deal drugs in those neighborhoods.
这个我不担保
I don't guarantee that.
我只担保谁贩毒我杀谁
I guarantee I'll kill anybody who does.
我来劝劝他 我来
Let me talk to him. Let me talk to him.
谁能拒绝艾图贝洛阁下
Who can refuse Don Altobello?
乔
Joe
不用
No!
我告诉你们
I say to all of you
今天 你们对我毫无尊重
I have been treated this day with no respect.
我替你们所有人赚钱
I've earned you all money.
我让你们发财
I've made you rich.
自己只要求少许
and I asked for little.
好啊你们不给
Good. You will not give?
那我就自己拿
I'll take.
至于柯里昂阁下…
As for Don Corleone
今天他讲得很清楚
well he makes it, very clear to me today
摆明与我为敌
that he is my enemy.
你们必须在我们两个当中选一个
You must choose between us.
乔 不要这样 乔
Hey Joey, no, Joey, no, Joey
大家可以坐下来谈
We can reason together.
拜托 麦克
Michael, Michael
我们慢慢谈
let's agree, huh?
他根本不知道自己刚才
He doesn't know what he's
不行
No, no no.
麦克 到处都有消息说
Uh, Michael, Michael. The news is everywhere.
你已经控制了"屹立"
Everyone is saying that, you control Immobiliare.
"屹立"已经在秘鲁洗黑钱了
Immobiliare already is laundering money in Peru
还有拿骚 我们都知道
and Nassau. We know that.
麦克 我们朋友也做了四十年了
Listen to me. We've been friends for 40 years.
我们也应该沾一点光
We should wet our beaks a little, huh?
我们想和你一起做生意
We want to do business with you.
- 好 - 用圣水洗净我们的钱
- That's right... - We can wash our money clean in the holy water of...
暗杀 快走 跟我来 快走
It's a hit. Let's go. Follow me. Let's get outta here!
- 我的外套 - 不要外套了
- My coat! - Forget your coat.
这是我的幸运外套 幸运外套
It's my lucky coat! It's my lucky coat!
跟在我后面
Stay right behind me!
麦克 走这边
Mikey, this way!
札萨 你这混帐东西
Zasa you son of bitch!
走 我们赶紧离开
Come on, we're outta here.
- 你干得很好 - 谢谢
- You did good. - Grazier.
所有老头目几乎全死了
The old Dons were pretty much wiped out.
幸存下来的也都改投乔札萨了
The ones that survived made deals with Joey Zasa.
艾图贝洛呢
Don Altobello?
他活下来了
He survived.
在他女儿斯达坦岛上的家里
He's with his daughters now in Staten Island.
他说要退隐 回西西里
Says he's gonna retire to Sicily.
没人撑腰 札萨决不会来这一手
Joey Zasa would never pull something like this without the backing.
他只会听人做事 其他什么都不会
He's just muscle. He's an enforcer. He's nothing.
用直升机行刺 他还想不出来这招
He doesn't have the wit for that helicopter attack.
他甚至都没那点野心和胆量敢消灭全帮
He doesn't even have the ambition to wipe out the whole commission.
我说我们要反击 也弄死他
I say we hit back and take Zasa out!
决不能让别人知道你在想什么
Never let anyone know what you're thinking.
传话给乔札萨
Well, let's get a message to Joey Zasa.
对于他所做的事情 我很敬佩
I respect what he's done.
长江后浪推前浪 真很正常
The new overthrows the old. It's natural.
你怎么能跟这种家伙做生意
How can you do business with this guy?
我现在首先是个生意人
I'm a businessman, first and foremost.
不想跟他再起冲突
I want no further conflict with him.
告诉他 我决定他的死活
You tell him from me that he can live or he can die.
文森 住口
Vincent, will you shut up!
好了
That's it.
乔札萨一个人干不出这种事
He can't be doing this alone.
我刚以为自己退出江湖了
Just when I thought I was out
又被拖回去
they pull me back in.
真正的大敌还没有露面呢
Our true enemy has not yet shown his face.
麦克 麦克
Michael! Michael!
挺住
No!
他有没有带药
Has he taken his medicine?
我不知道他吃什么药
I don't know what he took.
- 我能喘气了 - 快叫医生
- I've got my wind back. - Call a doctor.
- 快去 快去 - 文森
- Run, run! - Vincent!
快奔向雷电 雷声伤不了任何人
Run at thunderbolt. Thunder can't hurt.
声音伤不了任何东西
Harmless noise.
胡说八道
Bullshit.
他妈的老狐狸
You deceitful old fuck.
老艾 你个天杀的老狐狸
Altobello, you fuck!
弗雷德
Fredo!
天啊爸
Oh, God. Dad.
我通知凯
I'll call Kay.
先生 晚上好
Good evening, sir.
能不能停一下 我马上回来
Can we wait here? I'll be right back.
好的 先生
Certainly, sir.
你说有紧急事故 哈里森先生
Mr. Harrison, you said it was urgent.
你来告解过吗
Have you come to confess your sins?
柯里昂先生因糖尿病中风
Michael Corleone suffered a diabetic stroke.
我想见报之前应先通知你
I thought you should know that before you read it in the papers.
他现在昏迷不醒
He's in a coma on the critical list.
我来这里是为了确保我们的交易将不受任何影响
I'm here to insist the deal goes through in any event.
教皇的日子不多了
The pope has not much time left.
我跟你一样处境为难
So, as you, I am in a difficult position.
我们得尽早争取核准
We have to ratify this deal as soon as possible.
这一点我们有共识
We have an understanding.
很好
Good.
我现在要去医院
I'm going to the hospital.
我会为柯里昂先生祈祷
I'll pray for Mr. Corleone.
谢谢你
Thank you.
我们都会为柯里昂先生祈福
Our thoughts are with Mr. Corleone.
谢谢你神父
Thank you, Father.
如柯里昂一死 内幕会揭开
Everything will be out in the open if Corleone dies.
祈求我们能有更多的时间吧 凯斯济
Pray for time, Keinszig.
这是从我对永恒的长久思考中养成的习惯
A habit born of, a long contemplation of eternity.
文森 算了
Just forget about it, Vinnie
为什么算了 这很简单
Why forget about it? It's a simple hit.
我何尝不想干掉札萨
Look, I'd love to smack Joey Zasa then whack the fag, okay?
但不可能下手
But it's impossible.
他老在人群里
He's always mingling with people
还是在电视镜头前
in front of TV cameras
在自己的地盘上 我们不可能得手
in his own neighborhood. It's impossible.
－不 我们办得到 －怎么做
- It's not. It'll work for us. - How?
你以为他能让麦克叔活下去 换了你会吗
You think he's gonna let Uncle Michael survive this thing? Would you?
他也可能一病不起
He may not survive anyway.
你怎么下手
How would you do it?
我会亲自动手
I'd do it. I'd do it myself.
你去办
Do it!
- 你需要什么 - 派几个人给我
- What would you need? - See if you can get me a couple guys.
麦克
Hello, Michael.
是我 凯
It's Kay.
凯 想不到你会来
Kay, I never expected you to come.
我知道 知道
No, I know, I know.
- 但是我来了 - 我很高兴
- But I'm here. - I'm glad.
你知道
You know
我从来没见过你那么脆弱
this is the first time I've seen you look so helpless.
这没那么严重 真的
It's not so bad, really.
我反而觉得
I feel
我现在更聪明了
I'm getting wiser now.
- 是吗 - 是
- Yeah? - Oh, yeah.
病得越重越聪明 嗯
The sicker you get, the wiser you get, huh?
我死的时候会聪明绝顶
When I'm dead, I'm gonna be really smart.
麦克
Michael
安东尼的事要谢谢你
I want to thank you for Tony.
他表现得很好 非常受瞩目
He's doing really well. He's gotten some very good notices
而且复活节要在巴勒摩
and he's going to be making his operatic debut in Sicily
首次登台
in Palermo, this Easter.
所以 谢谢你
So, thank you.
在西西里老家献艺 那真是无上光荣
That's a real honor. In Sicily.
我会去的 不会错过
I will be there. I won't miss that.
决对不会
I won't miss that.
玛莉 安东尼 去看爸爸
Mary, Tony. Go see dad.
- 宝贝女儿 - 你会好起来的
- Oh, sweetheart. - Everything's going to be all right.
- 爸 - 安东尼
- Hey, dad. - Tony.
- 爸 你现在怎么样 - 过来
- How you doin' pop? - Come here.
你妈告诉我了 你演出的事
Your mother told me. She told me what happened.
巴勒摩登台的事 我真希望你能去
About Palermo? I really wanted you to be there.
当然要去 过来亲我一下
Of course. Come here, kiss me.
文森堂哥在吗
Cousin Vinnie?
他不在 你打他的公寓电话
No, he isn't here. Why don't you call his apartment
给他留个电话录音吧
leave a message on his machine?
你堂妹玛莉
It's your cousin, Mary.
让她进来
Let her in.
谢了
Thanks.
堂哥
Hey, cuz
顺便过来看看你 行吗
I just thought I'd drop by. Is that okay?
我去叫弟兄
I'm gonna get the guys.
不好 你不应该来的
No, it's not okay. You shouldn't have come.
只能呆几分钟 知道吗
A couple minutes only, okay?
- 你很漂亮 - 谢谢
- You look beautiful, cous. - Thanks.
这是你的俱乐部也是藏身之地
So this is your club, your hideout?
是的
Yeah
我只是来看一下
I came here to check it out.
家里只有我和姑姑 感觉很奇怪
It's so strange, just me and Aunt Connie in the house.
跟你在一起就好多了
I feel better when I'm with you.
怎么回事
What's wrong, sweetheart?
爸爸的事让我害怕极了
I'm really scared about my father.
不要怕
Don't be scared.
当我看到他被抬出救护车时 我以为他死了
When I saw them take him out of that ambulance, I thought he was dead.
我了解 但他会好起来
I know. Everybody says he's gonna be better.
不要担心了 嗯
Don't worry, okay?
我还记得小时候家里被乱枪扫射
I remember them shooting at our house when I was little.
纳利带了些保镖来
And Al Neri came one time with other bodyguards
只带我和安东尼离开了
and just took me and Tony away.
是不是那种事又发生了
Is it all happening again?
不是那样的
Not like that, sweetie.
那你为什么躲在这里 有什么事对你不利吗
Then why are you hiding here? Is something going to happen to you?
我不会出事的
Nothing's gonna happen to me.
我会照顾你
I'll take care of you.
我能跟你一起躲在这里吗
Can I stay here and hide out with you?
那你要为弟兄们做饺子
You have to make gnocchi for the boys.
明知道我不会做菜 不过我可以帮忙
You know I don't know how to cook, but I'll help.
- 好 - 该怎么弄
- Okay. - What do I do?
我爱你 堂哥
I love you, cuz
我也爱你 堂妹
I love you, too, cuz.
接着做吧
Okay, let's cook.
抱我
Hold me.
像你们这样在新闻界的人
You know the people like you in the press
或是警察都说什么黑手党 科萨·诺斯特拉
the police use words like Mafia, Cosa Nostra.
简直是笑话
This is a fantasy.
我们意裔人都是些伟大的人物
The Italian-Americans are great people.
我们辛苦建了这座城市 我们中有艺术家
We laid the bricks that built this city. We have the artists.
有发明电话的米乌奇
We have Meucci. He invented the telephone.
还有饰演米乌奇的
We have Don Ameche who played the guy
阿密奇阁下
who invented the telephone. Huh?
各位还是赶紧去买张抽奖券
So, listen, buy yourself a nice raffle ticket.
说不定还能赢辆凯迪拉克
Maybe win yourself a Cadillac.
这香肠真好吃
The salciccia is wonderful.
吃个三明治吧 我们走
Here, have a sandwich. Let's go.
- 札萨先生 你好 - 你好
- Nice to see you, Mr. Zasa. - Have a nice time.
别忘了去买抽奖券 嗯
Don't forget to buy your raffle tickets, huh?
你干什么
What are you doin'?
真抱歉 快过来
He's sorry. Come here, son.
好了 我们走
OK, OK, let's go.
乔 你好吗
Joey how are you, pal?
老弟 你好吗
Hey, how are you, Buddy Boy!
乔札萨 去你的
Hey, Joey Zasa! Joey! Up your ass!
那是谁 你认识
Who is this? You know him?
别理他
Ignore him.
喂 乔 谁会赢这辆汽车 你旁边的安特吗
Hey,Joey, who's gonna win the car? The Ant?
意裔美籍人的名声就是被这种人败坏的
This is the thing that gives the Italian-Americans a bad name, huh?
这种阉鸡败类
A caponi like this, huh?
去你的 乔
Hey,Joey, up your ass!
你他妈给我从车上下来 你有抽奖券吗
Get off of that fuckin' car. You got a raffle ticket?
看看我的奖券 好好看看
Take a good look at my raffle ticket here.
你的奖券不过这样而已
Here's what I think of you and your raffle ticket.
快给我滚开 小瘪三 快滚
I told you, get the fuck outta here, get outta here.
还想跑 乔你这狗东西
Run,Joey, you piece of shit!
开门 快开门
Open the door! Open the door!
乔 你好吗
Hi,Joe.
札萨
Zasa.
再也不准做这种事情
Don't ever again give that kind of order.
只要我活着就不行
Not while I'm alive.
懂吗
Understand?
你当时的情况根本不能做决定
You were too sick to make a decision.
纳利和康妮都同意我这么做
I got a go-ahead from Neri, I got a go-ahead from Connie.
康妮
Connie?
这个决定很正确 麦克叔
It was the right decision, Uncle Michael.
这是错误的决定
It was the wrong decision.
这个家我作主
I command this family.
不管是对的还是错的
Right or wrong
这都不是我想要的
it was not what I wanted!
明不明白
Do you understand?
明白
Yes.
够了 麦克
Come on, Michael.
懂了
Yes!
好 文森 扶我回床上
Good. Vincent, help me to my bed.
我要跟你谈一会
I wanna talk to you, alone, for a minute.
你知道
You know
对你 我总觉得有一分责任
I always felt responsible for you
你知道 你父亲
You know, your father
我大哥 我们兄弟对立
my brother, we were opposites.
我们总是吵架争辩
We would fight and argue
但我没有怀疑过他对我的爱
but I never doubted his love.
他愿意为我做任何事
He would do anything for me.
但他的脾气
But his temper
太急躁了
it was too much.
这总让他失去理智
Clouded his reason.
我不希望你也犯这种错误
I don't want you to make that mistak
另外
Also
他对女人也很有一套
he, too, had a way with women.
- 文森 你跟我女儿是怎么回事 - 我也这么听说
- Vincent, what are you doing with my daughter? - So I hear.
你跟她是怎么回事
What are you doing with her?
这太危险
It's too dangerous.
知道吗
You hear me?
好
OK.
文森
Vincenzo
敌人动手时
When they come
会向你所爱的人下手
they'll come at what you love.
麦克 你应该换一种生活了
Michael, you must lead another life.
人所能要求的你都拥有了
You have everything a man could desire.
是时候该退休了
It's time for you to retire.
我身上的责任太重
I have too much responsibility.
- 为"屹立" - 是的
- Immobiliare? - Si.
如今太棘手 你真的应该抽身出来
Too difficult now. You should really get out.
意大利那些权贵
What do you know
你知道多少
about those pezzonovante in Italy?
我年纪已经大了 对那些年轻人的事不了解
I'm too old to know anything about those new people.
我只能服老 回老家过清闲日子
I must accept my age and grow my olives and tomatoes.
我们还没那么老
We're not that old
但你的病很重
But you're very ill.
麦克
Michael
让我知道我能做些什么
Let me see what can be done.
让我帮你把路开得宽敞一点
Let me work to make your path a little easier.
你的友谊一直很有助益
Your friendship does that always.
那我就放心了
That makes me happy.
乔札萨 你看错他了
Joe Zasa, You were wrong about him.
我的毛病就是太容易相信别人
I trust too much. That's always been my fault.
麦克
Michael
到处都有背叛者
Treachery is everywhere.
你现在还有左右局势的能力
You still have your fingers on the strings, even now.
我们要多见面
Let's see more of each other.
麦克
Michael
在西西里见
In Sicily?
在西西里
In Sicily.
In Sicilia.
西西里
西西里 巴格里亚
你好吗
How are you?
班甸奴阁下 我的老朋友
Don Bendino, my old friend.
我带你们来这里
I wanted to bring you here
好让我的老朋友及庇护人
so that my old friend and protector
汤马西诺阁下
Don Tommasino
给我们出主意
could advise us.
汤马西诺阁下 你以为老艾如何
Don Tommasino, what do you think about Altobello?
他是个聪明人
A very talented man.
维持了我们西西里人
He has kept the peace between our Sicilian
与美国朋友之间的和平
and American friends.
讲道理的高手
The saint of reason.
亚特兰大城里的那次血洗行动
The bloodbath in Atlantic City
把纽约城搞得鸡飞狗跳
left New York a mess.
本来札萨想控制这个艰难的时局
Now, Joey Zasa at least was running a very tight ship
现在他死了 我们必须介入
but now that he's out of the picture, we're obligated to step in.
又回去
Step back in.
我们不去 迟早华人
If we don't, the Chinese
或者哥伦比亚人会趁虚而入
the Colombians will.
柯里昂家族从不贩毒
The Corleone's left drugs
所以纽约弱 巴勒摩强
so New York is weak, and Palermo is strong
你丢下的地方
Your enemies always get strong
敌人就能乘机坐大
on what you leave behind
汤马西诺阁下
Don Tommasino
谁可能指使那场屠杀
who could give the order for that massacre
而且还能在梵蒂冈的交易上施压
and still pressure the Vatican deal?
只有鲁加西
Only Lucchesi
能在黑白两道都吃得开
can reach between these two worlds.
我们的船必须朝同一个方向航行
Our ships must all sail in the same direction
几百年来意大利政界都有这种人
Italian politics have had these kind of men for centuries.
他们 才是真正的黑手党
They're, the true Mafia
大主教和梵蒂冈银行的事是个大问题
The Archbishop and the Vatican bank, that's the big problem.
是一样的
They're the same problem
他们之间有勾结
B.J., they're connected.
大主教有些权贵朋友
The Archbishop has very powerful friends.
他们会全力维护他
They totally protect him.
教会方面 我们有谁能够投靠吗
Is there someone in the church we can turn to?
德高望重的人
Someone we can tell our problem to.
红衣主教龙巴度
Cardinal Lamberto.
为人和善睿智
A wise and good man
极有影响力
very influential.
他会见你的
He will see you.
好 我会去拜见龙巴度枢机
Bene. I will go see this Cardinal Lamberto
看看这件事能不能以文明的方式了解
and see if we can work things out in a civilized way
就算你遵守协约
You honor your agreements
可是你要对付的那帮人全是些无赖
But these people you're dealing with are crooks
他们是不会守信的
they have no honor.
一切由我作主
My word is final.
政治与犯罪本来就是一回事
Politics and crime. They're the same thing
好 精彩
Bravo! Bravo, Bravo!
今天我邀请各位到此
I have invited you all here
是为了庆祝我的儿子首次登台演出
to celebrate, my son's first appearance in an opera house
他将于三周后
He will be appearing, in about three weeks
在玛西摩剧院登台
in the Theatre Maximo
演出"乡间骑士"
in the opera, Cavalleria Rusticana.
爸爸 是乡间骑士
It's Cavalleria Rusticana dad.
骑士看来我买错歌剧票了
Cavalleria. I think I've got tickets to the wrong opera.
我在纽约待得太久了
I've been in New York too long.
大家都会收到门票
Anyway, you will all receive tickets.
多多捧场啊
So come on down.
爸 我有一份礼物给你
Uh, dad, I've got a present for you
从柯里昂乡城流传而来
It comes from the town of Corleone and uh
是道地的西西里歌谣
it's authentic Sicilian
我 是为你学的
And uh, I learned it for you
她又漂亮又善良 我爱她
She was, wonderful, beautiful. I loved her.
然而她死了
And then she died.
我的亲信保镖
My trusted bodyguard
在我车上装炸弹
planted a bomb in my car
她却在我之前驾驶那辆车
she drove it before I did.
为什么在这么美丽的地方却充满了暴力
Why is such a beautiful country, so violent?
这是历史渊源
History.
妈妈告诉我说她以前最担心的
You know, mom was telling me about the old days
就是怕考试不及格
when her biggest worry was just passing exams
没错
Yes it was, then.
现在我为你担心
I worry about you now.
玛莉 你真是个心地善良的孩子 你总是这样
Oh Mary. Mary you're such a warm-hearted girl, you always were.
我爱我的家人
I love my family.
甚至是你的堂兄文森
Even your cousin Vincent?
我是真心爱他
I really love him.
他是你的近亲
He's your first cousin.
那我更加爱他
Then I love him first.
玛莉 你不能见他
Mary, you can't see him.
不要再见他了
Just don't see him any more
他说的对 太危险了
He's right. it's too dangerous
玛丽 听我说
Mary, listen to me.
你不能再见他了 不能以那种关系
You can't see him anymore. Not in that fashion.
不要
No.
- 答应我 - 不要
- Please promise me - No.
这件事你一定要答应
Obey me on this Mary!
不要 爸爸
No, dad!
玛莉是个聪明的孩子
Mary's smart, dad
她会明白的
she'll understand eventually.
美丽的堂妹 我的宝贝
你要见我
You wanted to see me?
是的
Yeah.
- 我要你去办件事 - 好的
- I want you to do something for me. - Okay.
这很危险
It's dangerous.
好 我做 要我做什么
Good. I'm in. What do you need?
我要你投靠艾图贝洛
I want you to sell your soul to Don Altobello.
背叛我
To betray me.
他不可能相信我 这里
He'll never believe me. Here.
- 那要看情形 - 坐下
- That depends. - Sit down.
我有办法
I have an idea.
你去探听老艾的关系攀到了多高
See if you can learn how high Altobello is connected.
安排一次见面
Arrange a meeting.
你说你对我忠心耿耿
You say how devoted you are to me.
再告诉他你的问题
Tell him your problems.
向他求助
You ask for his help.
什么问题
What problems?
说你想和我女儿私奔
That you want to run away with my daughter.
又怕这样会与我反目成仇
Only you know that if you do, I will become your enemy.
你知道我决不会这么做的 麦克叔
You know I'd never do that, Uncle Mike.
我知道
I know.
你求老艾来找我为你们说情
You ask Altobello to speak to me. To further the marriage.
你们毕竟是堂兄妹
You're cousins
麦克一向都保守
Michael was always a little old fashioned.
跟他说你不愿跟我做合法生意
Explain to him how, you can never be part of my, legitimate world.
要自立门户
That you want your own family.
我能接下札萨的摊子
straighten out with Joey Zasa
如果你能够说服他
If you could use your friendship to persuade him
我会永远记得你的恩情
I would be indebted to you forever.
柯里昂家的人
A Corleone
都非常重情谊
knows the value of such a friend.
那你肯为我做事
So, then, you would work for me?
是
Si.
记住
Remember
假如他暗示要你背叛我
if he hints that he wants you to betray me
你要装出收到侮辱的样子
get insulted.
他只是试探你
Because that's his trap.
你没有告诉我所有实情 文森
You're not telling me the whole truth, Vincenzo.
只要麦克一死 一切不都是由那个女孩儿继承
Isn't it true, with Michael gone, the girl controls everything?
你别扯上那女孩
You leave the girl out of this.
当然 你爱她 她也爱你
Of course, you love her. And she loves you.
我猜中了吧 文森
I guessed it Vincenzo, huh?
你是位智者 艾图贝洛阁下
You're a wise man, Don Altobello.
有好多事我要跟你学习
I'm going to be learning a lot from you.
最富有的人是拥有最多权贵朋友的人
The richest man is the one with the most powerful friends.
我有责任为你介绍
It's my duty to make the introductions.
鲁加西阁下
Don Lucchesi
老艾说你是个坚强的人
Don Altobello tells me you have good character, strong
是个值得人尊重的人
a man of respect.
这就是令札萨长眠的英雄
This is the hero who put Joey Zasa in his grave.
早认识他
If we'd known of his existence
我们就不会支持札萨了
we would never have backed Joey.
没有人会愿意的
No one wants another Joe
我们交个朋友吧
Let me be your friend.
最坚强的人也要交朋友
Even the strongest man needs friends.
这太荣幸了
I'm flattered.
但鲁西尼阁下你是金融政治人物
But you're a man of finance and politics, Don Lucchesi
那些事我都不懂
these are things I don't understand.
你知道怎么用枪吗
You understand guns?
金融就是一把枪
Finance is a gun.
政治
Politics
就是知道适时扣扳机
is knowing when to pull the trigger.
我要做些什么
How can I help?
追求和平的人总是受到赐福
Blessed is the peacemaker
因为他可以被称为是神的儿子
for he can be called a child of God.
- 懂说一点意大利语吗 - 懂
- Can you speak Italian well? - Yes.
汤马西诺阁下的轮椅
The wheelchair, for Don Tommasino.
这笔交易我托给了大主教
I trusted this business arrangement with the archbishop.
我那么相信他 相信他的诚实
I trusted him. I was sure his honesty was beyond a doubt.
但现在 我完全被骗了
But, as you see, I'm now the victim of a swindle.
他一直在拖延着我
He's stalling me.
巨额的钱财都到了政界高层手里
Vast money have gone to the pezzonovante in high political places
而梵蒂冈银行为其做担保人
and the Vatican Bank is the guarantor.
如过你说的话属实
If uh, what you say is true
这将是个大丑闻
there will be a great scandal.
你看这块石头
Look at this stone.
它泡在水里已经很久了
It has been lying in the water for a very long time
水却仍然没有能够浸透它
but the water has not penetrated it.
你看
Look.
还是干的
Perfectly dry.
欧洲人也是这样
The same thing has happened to men in Europe.
多少个世纪以来 他们一直受基督教教诲
For centuries they have been surrounded by Christianity
但基督却仍然没能进入他们的心里
but Christ has not penetrated.
不能与他们在生活中相伴
Christ doesn't breathe within them.
这是怎么回事
What's happened?
能不能 给我点甜的东西
Is it possible, that you could get me something sweet?
柳橙汁 随便什么 糖果
Orange juice, anything, candy.
我有糖尿病
Trouble with diabetes.
血糖一定要保持低水平
Blood sugar levels must be low.
我了解
I understand.
压力一大 有时候就这样
When I'm under stress sometimes this happens.
我了解
I understand.
来见你
I come to you
说这种敏感的事
on such a delicate matter
指控大主教
accusations against your Archbishop
对我而言太难受
was difficult for me.
精神收到折磨
The mind suffers
身体自然不好
and the body, cries out.
的确如此
That's true.
你要不要做告解
Would you like, to make your confession?
阁下
Your Eminence
我 我 很久没有做告解了
I'm uh, I'm uh, it's been so long
我不 不 不知道从哪里
I wouldn't, wouldn't, wouldn't know where to uh...
都有三十年了
it's been thirty years
我也许会耽误你很久
I'd, I'd, I'd use up too much of your time, I think.
拯救灵魂 我总是有时间的
I always have time to save souls.
我想 我已经罪无可赦
Well, I'm, I'm beyond redemption.
这里的教士也会向我告解
I hear the confessions of my own priests here.
有时候告解的心情已到极致
Sometimes the desire to confess is overwhelming
我们就要把握时机
and we must seize the moment.
假如我没有悔意
What is the point of confessing
告解有什么用
if I don't repent?
我听说你精打细算
I hear you are a practical man
你认为告解会有什么损失吗
What have you got to lose, huh?
说吧
Go on.
我
I
对妻子不忠
betrayed my wife.
说下去 孩子
Go on, my son.
背叛了自己的心
I betrayed myself.
我曾经杀过人
I killed men.
也曾令手下去杀人
And I ordered men to be killed.
接着说 孩子 接着说
Go on, my son, go on
这根本没用
It's useless.
说吧 孩子
Go on, my son.
我杀了
I killed
我让人杀了我的兄弟
I ordered the death of my brother.
他伤害了我
He injured me.
我杀了我母亲的儿子
I killed my mother's son.
我杀了自己的同胞兄弟
你的确罪大恶极
Your sins are terrible
因此你身心遭受苦痛
and it is just that you suffer
你的人生仍可获得救赎
Your life could be redeemed
但我知道你不相信
but I know that you don't believe that.
你也不会有所改变
You will not change.
教皇保禄六世
Pope Paul VI
罗马天主教廷至尊
the Supreme Pontiff of the Roman Catholic Church
于昨晚九时四十分辞世
died last night at 9:40pm
享年八十一岁
The Pope was 81 years old
教皇在过去几个月一直受病痛折磨
and had been in poor health for the last several months
康妮
Connie
我这一辈子都在力争上游
all my life I, kept trying to go up in society
希望成为一个干净清白的人
where everything higher up was legal, straight.
但是我爬得越高 世界就越险恶
But the higher I go, the crookeder it becomes.
这些事什么时候才能结束
How in the hell does it end?
千百年来人类相互残杀
Killing each other for centuries here.
为钱
For money
为名 为家族
for pride, for family.
为了免于沦为富贵者的奴隶
To keep from becoming the slaves of the rich pezzonovante.
我做了告解 康妮
I made confession, Connie.
坦白了我的罪行
I confessed my sins.
为什么 麦克 这可不像你的作风
Why Michael, that's not like you.
何必向一个陌生人坦白罪行
You don't have to confess your sins to a stranger.
这个人不一样
It was the man.
他是个好人
A good man.
真正的神父
A true priest.
他可以改变事物
He changed things.
麦克
Michael
你知道
you know
有时候我会想起弗雷多
sometimes I think of poor Fredo
淹死在湖里
drowned.
那是天意
It was God's will.
是个可怕的意外
It was a terrible accident.
但这已经过去了
But it's finished.
麦克 我爱你
Michael, I love you.
我永远都会在你这边
I'll always help you.
康妮
Connie.
艾图贝洛阁下 太荣幸了
I am honored, Don Altobello
你还从巴勒摩来探望我
that you've come from Palermo to visit me.
这孩子长大了
Hey, the little kid! He's grown.
学毛驴给我看
Do the donkey for me.
离我们当初一起做买卖
It's been some time
已经很久了
since we did business together.
套句美国话
You are my 'ace in the hole'
你是我盖着的王牌
as we say in America.
我有个麻烦
I have a stone in my shoe.
你能帮我除掉
You can remove it.
只有一个麻烦
Only one stone?
这一个就很危险
It's dangerous.
大名鼎鼎的人物
A famous man.
你要格外小心
You will have to take precautions.
要我做什么你说
Tell me what to do.
然后我会开价
Then I will tell you my price.
面包极品
Ah, what bread!
橄榄油
Ah, olive oil
无杂味
virgin
西西里独有
only in Sicily
敬你
A salute!
敬敌人
A morte!
凯
Kay!
康妮 你好吗
Oh, Connie! How are you?
玛莉 好想你
Mary, I've missed you!
- 麦克 你好 - 你好 凯
- Well, hello Michael. - Hello Kay.
妈 你看
Mom, look at this.
"乡间骑士"
可惜道格拉斯不能来
You know it's too bad that Douglas couldn't be with us.
他很想来
No, no, I know. He wanted to come very much
可是有重要的官司
but he had a very important trial.
我知道他一定想来
I know he wanted to come.
现在 你儿子是个艺术家了 嗯
Well, your son's an artist, huh?
是啊应该谢谢你
Oh yes. Thanks to you.
谢什么
Oh, what for?
谢你逼我放他走
For making me, let him go.
这样啊
Oh.
这么多年了
After all these years
我第一次来西西里
here I am in Sicily for the first time.
我帮你们照相
I want to get a picture of you together.
爸 微笑
Hey dad, smile.
纳利还在你身边 为什么
I see you still have Al Neri. Why?
我需要他啊他可以扶我上下车
Well, I need him. He helps me get in and out of the car.
帮我提公事包
Carry my briefcase.
你还在撒谎
You're still a liar Michael.
我来带你看看真正的西西里
Let me show you Sicily. The real Sicily.
这样也许你能更了解我们家的历史
Maybe you'll understand the family history a little better.
我了解的已经够多的了
Oh I think I understand it well enough.
拿着
Take them.
安东尼
Anthony
这是多年前你做给我的
I have something you made for me a very long time ago
它会给你带来好运
It may bring you luck.
你留下来了
You saved it, huh?
- 你还记得吗 - 记得
- Remember? - I remember.
谢谢你 爸爸
Thank you dad.
我为你骄傲
I'm proud of you.
谢谢
Thank you.
他们的身手靠得住吗
Are they as good as they look?
当然 一流高手
They're better. They're the best.
有他们在 麦克叔一定安全
As long as they're around, Uncle Michael is safe.
再见
Bye.
再见 告诉你爸我回来吃晚饭
Bye. Tell your father I'll be back for dinner.
好的
Okay.
玩儿的开心点
Have fun.
告诉安东尼等我
And tell Tony to be sure to wait for me.
好的
Okay. I will.
再见 妈妈
Bye mom.
早上好 夫人 请吩咐
Buon giorno, Signora. At your service
我见到爸爸会告诉他你走了
If I see dad, I'll tell him you left
像我父亲那样强大的人 在这个家族里只剩下你了
You are the only one left in this family with my father's strength.
假如麦克出事 我要你还击
If anything happens to Michael, I want you to strike back.
我会准备得妥妥当当
I'll have everything ready.
你发誓
You swear?
我发誓
I swear to you.
我父亲就是在这里出生
Here it is. The house where my father was born.
他们来到这里
This is where they came
掳走还是孩子的他 想把他杀掉
to take him when he was a boy. To kill him.
等等
Wait.
你听
Listen to that.
玛莉恋爱了
You know, Mary's in love.
是 我知道
Yes, I know.
是一个黑眼睛的英俊意大利男人
With a handsome young Italian man. Dark eyes.
我不允许这事
I won't allow it
这是错误的
It's wrong.
错误而且危险
It's wrong and it's dangerous.
父亲 我的父亲
Oh father, my father!
给我一点时间向主祈祷
Give me some time to pray to the Lord.
卡里尼男爵夫人不贞
The Baroness of Carini had betrayed her husband
同她的堂兄相恋
and fallen in love with her cousin.
不可饶恕
There will be no forgiveness!
她父亲举起宝剑
Her father stabbed her
将她一剑穿心
through the heart!
为了家庭的名声吗
Honor, huh?
我还记得当年你去见我父母
You know, I remember the time that you came to my parent's house.
你把我带进房里
And you took me into that room.
告诉我你的家族生意
And you told me about the family business
说你决不会沾手
and how you were never going to have anything to do with it.
那口气就像安东尼
You sounded like Tony
当年的我的确很像
I was a lot like Tony.
- 这里 凯 - 什么
- And there we see it. Kay. - What?
你来开车好吗
you mind driving?
出什么事了吗
No, what's wrong.
我的眼睛有时侯还好 有时候就
My eyes. Sometimes they're all right. But...
还有 我要去见汤马仙奴阁下
Listen, I have to see Don Tommasino
你好 夫人
Benday, signora.
看来今天没有随身保镖跟着啊
There's no bodyguards today.
我可是真的偷跑出来的
I really snuck away.
神父 上哪儿去 要搭便车吗
Father, where are you going? Would you like a ride?"
我认得你
I know you.
你是孟太利家的莫斯卡
You're Mosca of Montelepre.
以前当过杀手
You were an assassin then
现在也是
and you're an assassin now
我知道麦克·柯里昂在你家
I know Michael Corleone is at your house.
我会跟着你进去
I will pass through the gates with you.
卡罗 你好吗
How are you?
这是卡罗 我的老朋友
Kay, this is Calo, my old friend.
以前的保镖
One of my bodyguards in the old days.
- 我们可以在这里等他 - 要喝一杯吗
- We can wait here. - You want drink?
好的 我们进去
Yeah. Shall we go?
我以前在这里度过了很长时间
I spent a lot of time in this room
想念你
thinking of you.
然后你结婚了
And then you got married.
但我依然想念你
I still thought of you.
那间房里有什么
What's in that room?
麦克 你知道来这里很危险
You know this is dangerous for you, Michael.
这儿是西西里
This is Sicily.
我爱这里
I love this country.
为什么
Why?
世代以来
Well, all through history
这里的人受尽折磨
terrible things have happened to these people.
各种不公正的事
Terrible injustice.
但是他们依旧期待
But they still expect good
会有好的事情发生
rather than bad will happen to them.
就像我和你
Sort of like me and you, huh?
哪里
How so?
我现在在这里啊
Well I'm still here, right?
我们的过去也不很愉快
We do have a bad history
但我还在这里
but I'm still here.
是的 你还在 但是心里只有恐惧
Oh yes you are. But with dread.
说出你的心意
Gimme the order! C'mon!
为什么要这么做 让我不怕你
What's that supposed to do, is that supposed to make me not dread you?
我们来这里是为了看歌剧
We're in Sicily, the opera.
好吧
Okay
现在干什么
what do we do now?
讲道理
Be reasonable.
我希望我们不要再伤害彼此
Let's try not to hurt each other.
我希望你能原谅我
I want you to forgive me.
原谅你什么
For what?
所有事情
Everything.
像上帝那样
Oh, like God, huh?
不用那么夸张
Oh, I, I need something a little closer.
你当时不了解我的处境
You couldn't understand, back in those days.
我爱我的父亲
I love my father
我曾经发誓不会成为他那样的人
I swore I would never be, a man like him
但是我爱他 而他又身处险境
but I loved him. And he was in danger
我能怎么办
what could I do?
然后 你也身处险境
And then later, you were in danger.
孩子也一样 我能怎么办
Our children, were in danger. what could I do?
你们是我在这个世界上最重要的人
You were all that I loved, valued, most in the world.
但是我正在 已经失去了你
And, I'm losing you, I lost you, anyway.
你离开了我
You're gone.
我失去了一切
and it was all for nothing
所以
so
你要理解 我之后的人生都是注定的
you have to understand, I had a whole different destiny planned.
好吧 我不说了
All right, I'll stop.
麦克 我不知道你到底要我怎么做
I really don't konw what you want from me,Michael.
我真的不知道
I really don't know.
我是说
I mean
我并不是你想像的那种人
I'm not the man that you think I am.
我不知道
I dont't know.
我爱你 凯
I love you, Kay.
不要再害怕我
Don't dread me, anymore.
其实 在这里的每个晚上
You know, every night here in Sicily
我作梦
I dream
梦见我的妻子和孩子
about my wife and my children.
梦见我如何失去他们
And how I lost them.
如果这对你是种安慰我想告诉你
I guess, if it's any consolation, I want you to know that
麦克 过去我一直爱你
I always loved you, Michael.
以后是一样
I always, I always will.
出什么事了
What is it? What's wrong?
汤马西诺阁下被人枪杀了
They found Don Tommasino shot.
他死了
Is he dead?
我家主人死了 血债血偿
My master is dead. Blood calls for blood.
我一定要报仇
I must have revenge
将来也许有难事要你去办
Some day, you may have to do a difficult service for me.
尽管吩咐
Command me.
我会为他报仇
I will avenge him
计票
Totals
罗舒达 一票
Lorscheider, 1 vote.
塞里 十一票
Siri, 11 votes.
龙巴度 九十九票
Lamberto, 99 votes.
你是否接受推举
Do you accept your election
担任教皇圣职
as supreme pontiff?
上帝明鉴 赐福吾同僚之决策
My God, shed light on the decision they have taken on my behalf
我接受
I accept.
你希望被如何称呼
By what name do you wish to be called?
若望保禄一世
John Paul the First.
我将即刻执行此事
I will do things 'right away'
而不再考量拖延
rather than in 'a little while.'
梵蒂冈会计师凯斯济
Frederik Keinszig, known for a decade as "God's banker,"
已失踪三天 最后被见于
has been reported missing.He was last seen three days ago
梵蒂冈辖下
leaving the Rome offices of the Vatican owned
"屹立"的罗马办公室内
corporation International Immobiliare.
随之失踪的还有大笔款项 及多份文件
Also missing was a large sum of money, and several documents.
凯斯济快接电话啊白痴
Come on, Keinszig, you fool.
凯斯济的失踪
Mr. Keinszig's absence
使得梵蒂冈银行的交易越显蹊跷
casts further suspicion on the dealings of the Vatican bank.
多年以来该行及其下属子公司
For several years the bank and its subsidiary companies
都被指控进行
have been the object of allegations of
进行非法交易
disreputable business practices.
鲁加西 请你尽量要了解
Lucchesi, will you please try and understand.
我打电话找过他
I have phoned him.
也一直在等他的电话
I have waited here by the phone.
你一定要记住鲁西尼
You would do well to remember, Mr. Lucchesi
当今教皇的想法
that this Pope
与其上任大为不同
has very, different ideas from the last one.
再见 老朋友
Goodbye my old friend.
你本可以多活几年
You could have lived a little longer
我也可以更接近我的理想
I could be closer to my dream.
汤马西诺阁下 你深受爱戴
You were so loved, Don Tommasino.
为什么我招人畏惧
Why was I so feared
你却受人爱戴
and you so loved?
是什么原因
What was it?
我也做过不少好事
I was no less honorable.
我也想做好人
I wanted to do good.
到底是什么背弃了我
What betrayed me?
我的想法 还是我的心
My mind? My heart?
为什么我要逼迫我自己呢
Why do I condemn myself so?
我发誓
I swear
以我子女的性命发誓
on the lives of my children
给我赎罪的机会
Give me a chance to redeem myself
我再也不会犯下罪行
and I will sin, no more.
你脸色不好 有坏消息
You look pale. Bad news.
告诉我
Tell me right away
现在不仅是银行舞弊
It's not just a bad banking deal.
这些人就是屠夫
These guys are butchers.
哪些人
What guys?
鲁加西
Lucchesi.
他控制了所有人
He controls all of them
包括老艾
Altobello
大主教
the Archbishop
还有其他更高的人
other people higher up, P2, maybe
还有秘密不知道
Secret, unknown.
他们正在做什么事情
They're running things.
我是他们的障碍
I'm in their way.
他雇了职业杀手要杀你
He's hired a professional assassin to kill you.
是西西里人
He's Sicilian.
不知道名字
I don't know his name
据说他从没有失手过
but they say he never fails.
我们都很危险
Then no one is safe.
新教皇的处境也很危险
Even the new pope is in danger.
我们还来得及阻止
We still have time. We can prevent this.
我尽力了
I tried
我已经尽力
想避免走到这田地
to keep everything from coming to this.
但是躲不开
But it's not possible
在世上躲不开
not in this world.
下命令吧
Give me the order.
那你就没有回头路了
You won't be able to go back.
你会步我的后尘
You'll be like me.
好啊
Good.
我一辈子都想脱离江湖
All my life I wanted out.
希望我的家庭远离是非
I wanted the family out.
我不想
Well, I don't want out.
我渴望拥有保护这个家族声誉的权利
I want the power to preserve the family.
下命令吧
I'm asking for the order.
行了
It's done.
我干不下去了
Because I can't do it anymore.
没关系
Well, it doesn't matter.
文森会处理的 出去吧
Vincent knows what to do. Come on outside.
歇会儿 不要再想了
Take a rest and don't think about it.
我能做的就是一直思考
All I do is think about it.
我就是你的儿子
I'm your son.
一切交给我
Command me in all things.
放弃我女儿
Give up my daughter.
这是你要付的代价
That's the price you pay
为你选择的人生
for the life you choose.
侄子
Nephew
从今以后
from this moment on
你就是文森柯里昂
call yourself Vincent Corleone.
坐下
Sit.
文森阁下
Vincenzo.
康妮 谢谢
Grazie Connie.
柯阁下
Don Corleone.
文森柯里昂阁下
Don Vincenzo Corleone.
玛莉
Mary.
"乡间骑士"歌剧
文森
Et Tu, Vincenzo
你对麦克的感情我了解
I know how you feel about Michael
但你救不了他
but you, you can't save him.
他失败了
He's lost.
为自己打算吧
Think of yourself.
你的答案是什么
What's your answer, Vincent?
欣赏歌剧
Enjoy the opera.
一切都安排妥当
It's all taken care of.
察看一下酒吧 我去检查屋顶
Check the bar. I'll check the top floor.
但愿安东尼在台上演唱
Here's hoping Tony sings better at Theatre Maximo
胜过他在洗澡时的歌声
than he does in the shower.
亲爱的康妮
My darling, Constanzia.
艾图贝洛阁下
Oh, Don Altobello.
这真是件大事
This is a great occasion.
来 坐
Come and sit down.
生日快乐
Happy birthday.
八十岁的人看来像六十
You're eighty years old.You don't look more than sixty.
我的生日只有你记得
You're the only one who remembered.
刚得到的消息
Michael, we just got the word.
"屹立"的交易教皇签署了
The Pope's ratified the Immobiliare deal.
我们赢了
We've won.
恭喜
Congratulations.
世事的发展还真是奇妙
How strange, the way things work.
正如你所预言的
The Pope's doing exactly what you said he'd do
教皇清理门户了
he's cleaning house.
他应该谨慎
He should be careful.
做诚实的人也会有危险
It's dangerous to be an honest man.
加派人手到后台保护安东尼
I wanna put a little more muscle backstage with Tony
你过以前生日总请我吃东西
On your birthday, you used to shower me with treats.
奶油卷
Tootsie Rolls!
制奶油卷的修女发誓缄口
The nuns who made these cannolis took a vow of silence.
手艺绝世
They're the very finest.
堂妹
Hey, coz.
你的皮外套呢
Where's your leather?
别说了
Stop it.
你这么瘦 给你吃
You're so thin. You eat it.
不错 谢谢
E buono. Grazie, grazie.
结束了 玛莉
It's over, Mary.
我有很多事要做 不能连累你
There are things I have to do that you can't be a part of.
这与你爸无关 这是我的决定
Don't look at your father, it's not your father's decision, it's mine.
不要恨你爸
Don't hate your father.
我想投入的事业不能让你呆在我身边
There are things I'm going to be part of, you can't be around.
今夜之后 你再也不会见到我
After tonight, you won't see me anymore.
不要
No.
你要谅解 玛丽
You gotta understand, Mary. You gotta understand.
我永远爱你
I'll always love you.
爱别人吧
Love somebody else.
敬安东尼 敬安东尼
To Tony! To Tony!
今晚不会动手了
They won't try anything
嗯 一切都很正常
Yeah,everything's fine. It's all clear out here.
我已经派纳利去了梵蒂冈
I've already sent Al Neri to the Vatican.
- 鲁加西公馆 - 是
- Mr. Lucchesi's house? - Si.
麦克柯里昂派我传信
I bring a message from Michael Corleone.
让他进来
Let him in.
晚安
Good evening.
今天晚上柯氏家族要算帐
Tonight the Corleone family settles its accounts.
凯斯济
Keinszig
小小的瑞士银行家
that little Swiss banker fuck
一直都就在玩弄大家 妈的
he's been swindling everyone from the beginning. Fuck 'im.
鲁加西阁下 我的朋友
Don Lucchesi.My friend
卡罗会去拜访他
Calo will pay him a visit at his home.
纳利
Neri
搭火车去罗马
take a train to Rome.
为大主教点根蜡烛
Light a candle for the Archbishop.
教皇 要茶吗 可以安眠
Tea, your holiness? It will help you sleep.
文森柯里昂送来的
This is from Vincent Corleone.
麦克 不好了
Michael, it's serious.
线人说有要人谋害教皇
Our man inside the Vatican says there's a plot against the Pope.
你是说他会心脏病发
You mean he's going to have a heart attack in the night.
教皇有强大的敌人
This Pope has powerful enemies.
我们可能来不及救他
We may not be in time to save him.
回去听戏
Now let's go back to the opera.
教皇
Eminenza?
教皇死了
The Holy Father is dead!
睡吧
Sleep.
睡吧 教父
Sleep, Godfather.
说话 告诉我
Speak...tell me.
你已丧失
You have lost
失去人心
the faith of the people.
靠人心立业就是建在烂泥之上
He who builds on the people builds on mud.
柯里昂的口信呢
And Michael Corleone's message?
这很重要
It's very important.
我只能告诉你一个人
I must whisper it in your ear.
他没带武器
He's clean.
权力会耗尽没有权力的人
Power wears out those who don't have it.
- 我喜欢这出戏 - 我就知道
- I like this opera. - Yeah I figured you would.
- 精彩 去打个招呼 - 谢谢你
- Bravo. Say hello. - Thank you.
我能跟你谈谈吗
Can I please talk to you now?
不行 现在不行
Not now Mary, it's not a good time.
你听起来就像我爸
You're just like my father.
快 跟你的家人呆在一起
Come on, stay with the family. Go on.
- 说话 - 双胞都挂了
- Talk to me. - The twins are dead.
一分钟内
In about one minute
警察就会包围这里
there's going to be carbanieri crawling all over this place.
知道了 带所有人上车 不动声色地
Okay. Let's get everybody to the cars. Nice and quiet.
提起柯里昂
When they hear the name Corleone
大家会想起歌声
they're going to think of that voice.
爸
Dad?
爸 为什么这样待我
Dad? Why are you doing this to me?
退开
Stay back.
你不要这样对我
You don't have to do this to me, please.
怎样对你 亲爱的 你在说什么
Doing what, sweetheart. What do you mean?
玛莉 过来见
Mary, please...
爸
Dad?
不要
NO!
玛莉 不要
NO! Mary!
天啊 不要
Oh, God. Oh, God, NO!
求求你 不要
Oh, God, no, please!